Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太＞
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
ひびと
＜栄光の日生まれの弟･日々人は➡
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
日本人初の
ムーンウォーカーとなった＞
＜月面望遠鏡建設を望む恩師･
シャロンとの約束を果たすため➡
Older brother Mutta seeks to become an astronaut, and keep his promise to former teacher Sharon,
兄･六太は宇宙飛行士を目指す＞
to build a telescope on the moon.
＜選抜試験を辛うじて突破するが
訓練中もトラブルの連続！＞
Mutta's made it through the first round, but he keeps running into trouble.
＜筆記試験では最低点｡
暴走教官が➡
On the written test, he scores the lowest.
And as a result, he's assigned to a wild flight instructor.
飛行訓練の担当になる始末＞
＜だが 困難に揉まれたおかげで
宇宙飛行士の大事な資質を➡
However, the older brother Mutta
has yet to realize that he's rapidly learning the lessons he'll need to become an astronaut.
猛スピードで
身に付けていることに➡
兄･六太は まだ気づいていない＞
(ｼﾞｮﾝ)体調はどうだ ヒビト｡
なんば
(南波日々人)ああ バッチリだよ｡
How are you doing, Hibito?
Oh, I'm fine.
(ｼﾞｮﾝ)朝メシは食ったか？
軽くね｡
Did you have any breakfast?
Some.
(ｼﾞｮﾝ)アッハハハ そいつは
グッドでナイスだ｡➡
That's good and nice.
調子がいいなら なによりだ｡➡
Glad to hear you're doing well.
ＯＫ ＯＫ！
まあ 気楽にやろうぜ～！
Okay, okay.
Let's take it easy.
いいか ヒビト｡今回に限っては➡
Listen up, Hibito...
This time, we want you to do the opposite of what you'd normally do in this training.
普段の訓練の時とは
真逆のことを言うぞ｡
この中を宇宙だと思うな｡
Don't act like you're really in space.
もちろん月面でもない｡
ヒューストンにある➡
And don't act like you're on the moon's surface.
You're just taking a dip in a nice Houston pool.
ゴキゲンな ただのプールだ｡
いいな｡
Got it?
ＯＫ ジョン サンキュー｡
Okay, John.
Thank you.
(ｼﾞｮﾝ)よし じゃあ
ヘルメットをかぶせるぞ｡
Then put on your helmet!
プールに降ろすぞ ヒビト！
We're dropping you in the pool, Hibito.
Okay.
ストップ！中止だ！止めろ！
Stop! Training's off!
Halt the drop!
What?!
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)なに!?
中止だ 中止！引き上げろ！
We're calling it off!
Pull him out!
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)急げ！
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)手をかせ！
Hurry!
Give me a hand!
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)こっち 早く！急げ！
Over here! Quickly!
(ｼﾞｮﾝ)早く上げろ！
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)こっちへ 早く！
Get him out of the water!
This way!
Quickly!
すぐにヘルメットを外せ！
Get that helmet off!
大丈夫か ヒビト！
ヘルメットを外すぞ！
You okay, Hibito?
We're removing your helmet.
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
It's just obvious that the more you put in your bag
The heavier it gets
The harder I work, the closer I get to my goal
But I'm just not getting there fast enough
I gaze at the night sky but it doesn't calm me down
Now that you've heard how loud my heart's beating
Let's take a trip outside
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of dreams and reality
I'm currently updating the canvas of my dreams
With a glittering universe and a blue earth
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of facades and honesty
I'm currently conversing with the canvas of my dreams
On this orbit of fate
With a fire in my belly
#72 Hibito's Disorder
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ｡
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
《何でだよ…クソッ！
これじゃあ…》
Why is this happening, damn it?!
At this rate,
《船外活動なんて
できるわけない!!》
I'll never participate in EVA again...
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)医師の見解では
ヘルメットの閉塞感が➡
The doctors believe that the helmet's confined space is triggering the panic attacks.
パニック発作を
誘発してるのだろうということだ｡
君も知っての通り
月ミッションのクルーには➡
As you're well aware,
crew members on lunar missions are required to be available for EVA.
船外活動の技能が
必須条件となっている｡➡
残念だが ヒビト
船外活動ができないうちは➡
I'm sorry to have to tell you this, Hibito.
But we can't send you on lunar missions if you can't participate in EVA.
君を月ミッションには
加えられないんだ…｡
この変な症状…必ず治します｡
I'm going to find a way to get rid of this disorder.
それまで このことは
医師と僕たちだけの話に➡
In the meantime, can you keep this a secret among you, me, and the doctors?
留めておいてもらえますか｡
うちの家族 特に兄には…｡
Tell my family, particularly my brother...
僕は あくまで
月の訓練を続けていると…｡
that I'm still training for lunar missions.
了解した｡医師連中にも➡
Understood.
I'll have the doctors report that you suffer from a temporary physical condition.
一時的な体調不良で通すように
伝えておこう｡
だが ヒビト
嘘をつき通すのは…しんどいぞ｡
However, Hibito...
It will be difficult to maintain that lie.
(小林)あ！しまった｡
私 マフラー忘れました｡
Ah...
Darn, I forgot my scarf.
ハハハッ ロシアは寒いよ｡
Russia really is cold.
(小林)ですよね！
私 パパッと買ってきます｡
It is... I'll go buy one real fast.
あっ！ちょ ちょっと 勝手に
どっか行かないでよ 小林さん！
Ah...
D-Don't run off by yourself, Kobayashi!
あれ…珍しいですね 日々人さん
キャップなんか かぶって｡
Oh, this is unusual, Hibito...
You never wear hats.
だって周り見てよ｡
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡ目的らしき➡
Look around us...
Lots of Japanese tourists are here due to NASA.
日本人観光客が いっぱいいるよ｡
あ…ほんとだ｡➡
Oh, you're right.
Is Hibito around?
たしかに 見つかったら
サイン攻めにあいますね あれは｡
If you're spotted, you'll be signing autographs for the rest of the day.
アニメの影響もありますもんね！
The cartoon doesn't help matters.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)すごわね～これ！
This is amazing...
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)こんなに鍵盤 軽いのに
本物のピアノの音みたい｡
The keys are so light,
but it still sounds like a real piano.
楽しい！
I'm really enjoying this.
ありがとう｡
Thank you.
Sure.
《シャロン 実は俺…》
Actually, Sharon...
《もしかしたら もう 月へは…》
I might not get to return to the moon.
《言えるわけねえか…》
I can't tell her that.
ねえ ヒビト…何か話したいことが
あるんじゃないの？
Say, Hibito...
Is there something you want to tell me?
どうしたの？ヒビト｡
What's wrong, Hibito?
If something's bothering you, you can tell me.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)何かあるなら
話していいのよ｡
あのさ…｡
Well...
現在
A panic disorder.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)パニック障害？
ああ｡治るかどうかは
人に よるんだって｡
Yeah, they say that some recover and some don't.
じゃあ 治るわよ
ヒビトなんだから｡
Then you'll get better... That's who you are, Hibito.
話してくれて ありがとう
ヒビト｡
Thank you for telling me, Hibito.
ヒビトも 闘ってるのね｡
You're fighting hard, too.
なあシャロン このことは
ムッちゃんには…｡
Hey, Sharon...
Don't tell Mu about this.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)大丈夫 わかってる｡➡
Don't worry, I understand.
ヒビトは ずっとそう｡
何があっても ムッタの前には➡
You've always been that way.
No matter what happens, you want to act like nothing is wrong around Mutta.
何事もなかったみたいに
戻りたいのよね｡
《早く治さねえと
いずれバレちまうよな…》
If I don't get better soon, everyone will notice.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)そこで大事なのが
きみつせい
気密性が しっかり➡
Remember it's critical to check that it's airtight.
保たれているかチェックすること｡
それを怠ると やっかいな事になる｡
If it isn't, you'll be in big trouble.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)特に レゴリスだ｡そいつは
確実に 除去するんだ｡
Regolith is a real concern.
Make sure you've cleared it all off.
What if regolith gets inside the spaceship?
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)もし 船内に
入ってしまったら？
Kenji and Nitta are so lucky.
(南波 六太)
《いいな～ ケンジと新田｡
俺も月面モジュールの➡
Man, I want to train in the lunar module...
訓練やりてぇな～｡
チクショー｡はぁ～…》
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)おう ムッ君！
あ…おう！
Hey, Mu!
Hey...
にった
(新田)よう！久しぶりだな
南波！
Yo, haven't seen you in a while!
そっちは どうだ？
How's it going on your end?
フッフッフッ…めちゃくちゃ
楽しいね バギー作り｡
I'm having the time of my life making buggies.
代わってやりたいぐらいな｡
I wish you could experience it.
あ…約束の時間か｡ごめん ムッタ
あと１５分程待ってて｡
Oh, is it time?
Sorry, Mutta...
Could you wait fifteen minutes?
あ…そうなの｡
Oh... Really?
とまあ このように
数えあげたら➡
So as you can see, the moon has more dangers than you can count.
きりがないほど
月面では…｡
やっぱり全然違うなぁ｡月だと
重力 ６分の１だし｡➡
It's completely different...
The moon's gravity is a sixth that of Earth.
その上 空気抵抗による
抑えつけも ないからね｡➡
And there isn't any air resistance...
スピードを上げると すぐ
車体が浮き上がるんだ｡➡
If you accelerate, the vehicle goes airborne.
ちょっとした
デコボコなんかでね｡
It's a rough ride.
今みたいなのは ザラだよ｡
地球だと こんな風な➡
Stuff like that happens all the time.
On Earth, it's only a little bump...
揺れになるんだけど
月だとね➡
But on the moon, it's kinda like an awkward way to skip.
へたくそな
スキップみたいになる｡
⦅イエーイ！イエーイ…！⦆
Yay! Yay! Yay! Yay!
なるほど｡
I understand.
If you want to improve the handling or the brakes' efficiency,
ハンドリングにしても
ブレーキの利きにしても➡
改善するためには 浮かないように
車体を重くするしかないかな｡
you'll have to make the body heavier, to keep it from becoming airborne.
…だそうだ｡
There you go.
(通信:六太)聞いてた？ピーター｡
Hear that, Peter?
(ﾋﾟｰﾀｰ)ああ｡すんばらしい
アイデアだ｡
Yeah, that's a wonderful idea...
まったく これだから
宇宙飛行士という生き物は…｡➡
Man, this is why astronauts are no help.
上から散々 軽量化 軽量化と
言われた末の➡
The body's light because the brass keeps asking us to minimize the weight.
あの 骨々ボディだってこと…｡
だれか 彼らに説明してあげて！
Can someone explain that to them?
仮に あとプラス５０キロで車体の
浮きを抑えられるとしよう｡➡
Let's assume another fifty kg would keep the buggy from going airborne.
月での50キロは すなわち
地球では ６倍の300キロだ｡
Fifty kg on the moon times six is three hundred kg on Earth.
Any idea how much it costs to send three hundred kg to the moon?
300キロの荷物を 月に送るのに
いくら かかると思う？
I know the answer, but go ahead.
俺は知ってるけど…
言ってやれ いくらよ？
How much?
２億ドルだ｡
Two hundred million dollars.
そうなるよね～｡
Of course...
《つまりは 200億円か…》
That's around twenty billion yen.
(ダン)軽量化こそが 僕らの
使命みたいなもんだよね｡➡
One of our mandates is to keep the buggy light...
だから 風の吹かない月では
いらない フロントガラスを取り➡
Since there's no wind on the moon, we removed the windshield,
屋根を取り ドアを取り
今の あの姿になったわけだし｡
removed the roof,
and removed the doors, arriving at the current design.
A buggy that won't fall, huh?
落ちないバギーか…
ん～ チクショウ！
Damn...
ん？子供の頃さ 未来じゃ
車も空飛んでると思ってたけどな｡
When I was little, I figured we'd have flying cars in the future.
実際には そうでもなかったな｡
But that didn't happen.
Ah, I like it!
あっ いいかも！
バギーも 空飛ばしちゃう？
We can make the buggy fly?
Hey, that'll put us over budget.
コストオーバーでしょ？➡
Assuming it's even possible.
もし 実現したとしても｡
砂を まき散らしながら進む➡
We'd end up with a vehicle that sends sand flying everywhere...
大迷惑な乗り物の完成だ～｡
でも取りあえず 一案として
提出してみるのは➡
For now, we can keep it on the table.
いいんじゃないか？
ほかにも 何案か出して➡
Float that and a few more ideas by HQ, and they'll give us a budget.
あとは 本部が
予算を見て決めることだ｡
Oh...
何の｢あ｣よ？
Oh, what?
解決できるかもしれない案を
思いついたかもしれないの ｢あ｣｡
Oh, I might have a solution to our problem.
Oh.
ゴホン！
(後輩)はい ミラクルカー
コーポレーションです｡
Yes, this is the Miracle Car Corporation.
はい…｡え？➡
Yes.
Huh?
南波先輩!?
南波くん？
Nanba?
Eh?
までら
Hmm?
俺が昔 大ボツくらった
飛行自動車の…｡そう➡
Remember the flying car I designed that was scrapped?
Yes, are those blueprints still around?
あれの企画データって
まだ残ってる？
あ じゃあ
こっちに送ってもらっていい？
Great, could you send them over?
はせい
それとさ そっちから派生した
例のフロントガラスのやつって➡
And are you almost done with the windshield that came from that design?
そろそろなんだよね？
(後輩)はい はい…｡
Yes... Yes.
Is that Nanba on the phone?
南波くんが かけてきたのか？
僕にも ちょっと話させて｡
Let me talk to him.
Oh... Hello?
あ～ もしもし 先輩？ちょっと
間寺役員と内線代わりますね｡
I'm going to put Director Matera on.
Eh? I don't think that's...
えっ!?いや それはまぁ…｡
《おい おい おい…》
Hold on...
Zidane!
《どーしよ まだ根にもってたら》
Now what?
What if he still holds that against me?
(間寺)僕だよ南波君 間寺です｡
久しぶり｡
It's me, Nanba.
This is Matera.
Been a long time.
あ お久しぶりです｡
Yeah, it's been a long time.
いやぁ～まさか君が
宇宙飛行士になるとはねぇ｡
I never expected you to become an astronaut.
いや～ビックらこいた
ビックらこいた｡
Yes, I was very surprised.
でもね 南波君
僕は君のそういう素質を➡
However, Nanba...
I always knew you had the potential.
ちゃ～んと見抜いていたんだよ｡
What?
≪えぇ～!?≫
No, I'm serious.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](間寺)
いやいやホント 僕の期待通りに
成長してくれたね｡➡
You've come a long way, just as I foresaw...
だからまぁ ある意味では➡
So you could say that firing you was the correct decision.
君をクビにしたのは
間違いではなかったね｡➡
うん結果オーライだよね うん｡
Ultimately, everything worked out!
ところでさぁ ウチの娘が
れいじ
あの新田零次さんのファンなんだ｡
By the way, my daughter is a fan of Nitta Reiji.
君からサイン
お願いできないかなぁ？
Could you ask him for an autograph?
なんだ？
ヒソヒソ話してる｡
What's he saying?
Can't tell because he's whispering.
わ わかりました｡
S-Sure...
《これはチャンスだ》
This is my chance!
ん？ほうほう あぁ～いいとも！
Hmm? Oh?
That's fine.
We'll assist in any way that we can.
ウチに出来ることなら
何だって協力するよ｡
ほう…ほう…｡➡
Ah... Ah.
ろうば
老婆の改良？おばあちゃんの？➡
Improving Rover?
You mean your dog?
Oh, you mean the lunar rover! I knew that!
あっローバーね！だと思った！
車のプロの実力を
ぜひ宇宙で役立てたいんです｡
I'm excited to send professional engineering into space.
んん！なるほど そういう事なら
ぜひ協力させてもらうよ｡
Yes, I get your drift...
You can count on our support.
あぁ 男に二言はノーだ！
Yeah, you have my word!
ではまた はいはい｡
I'll speak to you again!
Got it!
あっ 例のヤツお願いね｡
Don't forget your promise.
Yes, got it.
かわいい元社員の頼みだ｡
断れまい｡
I can't turn down a request from a former employee.
ＮＡＳＡのローバー開発に
協力することになった｡➡
We'll be helping NASA to develop their new rover.
格安で｡
At a cheap price.
ほしか
よし 次は星加さんだ｡
Okay, next up is Hoshika.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](六太)
あ もしも～し南波で～す｡
Oh, hello?
This is Nanba...
あづま
(吾妻)バトラー室長も
ご存知のはず｡
Director Butler, you were there.
日々人の命を救う
決め手になったのは➡
You know that Hibito's only alive because of his brother Mutta's advice.
兄･六太の的確な助言でした｡
それだけでも
十分 評価に値することです｡
He deserves a great deal of credit.
なぜ六太に 希望の月の訓練を
させないんですか？
So why won't you let Mutta train for a lunar mission, Director?
室長！
《怖い…》
Scary.
まぁ本当のことを言うと➡
Well, to be honest, I'd love to send both brothers to the moon.
私だって兄弟そろって
月へ行かしてやりたいと思ってる｡
兄弟で月に立てなかった
エディとブライアンの➡
Because I remember how it was for Eddie and Brian.
無念も知ってるからな｡
だが医師と相談して
決めたことだ｡
But I made this decision after talking to the doctors.
ヒビトに障害がある以上➡
If Mutta begins training for a lunar mission while Hibito is suffering from a disorder,
ムッタが月の訓練を
始めるということは➡
ヒビトの焦りと不安をあおり➡
Hibito will only feel more pressure,
パニック障害治療の
妨げになってしまうんだ｡
and curing him will be harder.
俺は逆だと思いますけどね｡
I think they have it backward.
室長！プレゼンの時間です｡
Director, it's time for the presentation.
ああ今 行く｡
Yes, I'm coming.
Last week, your Mutta and Peter were wanting to make a presentation...
先週あたりから噂のムッタと➡
ピーター達がプレゼンを
したいと言ってきててね｡
ローバーの改良案だ｡
どうせ却下だろうがな｡
They have a proposal for an improved rover.
It'll probably be shot down.
君も行くか？
Care to join me?
プレゼンを始めるにあたって➡
Mutta has a request to make before the presentation begins.
ムッタさんから
ご要望がありまして｡
ふむ｡
Hmm?
If you like the proposal and deem it feasible,
(職員)もし この改良案を
気に入っていただけて➡
実現可能と判断された場合➡
月の訓練への参加を
検討していただきたいとの事です｡
he wants you to let him train for a lunar mission.
ふん ずいぶん強気だな｡
Heh, he sounds pretty confident.
まぁ そんな約束はできんが｡
Well, I can't make any promises.
Here we are.
お待たせ｡
It's been so long since I looked up at the moon
Though it's always keeping a cold eye on me
Yeah, it always keeps a cold eye on me
I wanna rough up this rotten way home
But even if it makes me mad
I can't take my eyes off it. Yeah, I can't take my eyes off it
I can't take my eyes off that dazzling smile
What did I want back then?
What was I looking for?
I should've known my tears would take me to my dreams
Blow this gloomy reality away for me
I want to see how tiny our huge worries seem
From up in that dark ocean of space
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#73 A Road on the Roadless Moon
Time to present our proposed buggy that won't fall!
＜落ちないバギー開発の
プレゼンが ついに始まった＞
＜月での事故をなくすために
必要なのは こちら➡
This is our proposal to eliminate accidents on the moon!
月面ナビシステムです＞
(役員)＜何だね？そりゃ＞
The lunar navigation system.
What's that?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"A Road on the Roadless Moon"
Mr. Hibbit!
(ヒビット)うおぉ～！
Yay!
イェーイ！
やぁ みんな僕ヒビット！
Hey, everyone! I'm Hibbit!
It looks like I need lots of training to go to the moon!
月へ行くためには
色んな訓練が必要なんだって｡
Want some carrots?
ニンジン食べる？
Ah!
イェッ！ イェッ！ イェッ…｡
Yeah!
Yay!
イエー！イエー！イエー…｡
(バディゴリラ)おい こんな洞窟に
何があんだ？
Hey, what are we looking for in this cave?
There's a legendary astronaut here.
ここに居るらしいんだ
伝説の宇宙飛行士が｡
(コウモリ)ギャア ギャア ギャア｡
うわぁコウモリとかヤダ！
I hate bats!
Ah! Hey, Hibbit!
あっ！おいヒビット！
Oh!
どうした？ん？
What is it?
だ 誰だお前は！
Wh-Who are you?
私はフレディドッグ｡
I am Freddy Dog.
君達が来るのは分かっていたよ｡
I've been expecting you.
私は鼻がきくんでな｡
I have a sharp nose.
Bow wow...
あ ワン｡
Bow wow.
キミなんか頼りになりそう｡
You look dependable.
Will you join us?
僕達の仲間になって
くれないかい？
私は仲間になれと言われて➡
I'm not so easy that I'll join just because you ask.
すぐになるほど
軽い犬ではない｡
Want some carrots?
ニンジン食べる？
ニンジンに釣られるほど➡
I'm not so easy that I'll join because you offer carrots.
軽い犬でもない｡
Oranges
(ヒビット)フレディとってこ～い｡
Freddy, go fetch!
ワン ワン ワン！
ワォ～ン！
(２人)軽っ！
That was easy.
See you next week!